Dear friends,
I have the joy
of being able to tell you
that I spent a glorious hour last night
listening over the radio
to Beethoven's ninth symphony.
Last night, when the family was listening
to your wonderful rendering
of the immortal symphony,
someone suggested that I put my hand
on the receiver and see if I could
get any of the vibrations.
He unscrewed the cap
and I lightly touched
the sensitive diaphragm.
What was my amazement to discover
that I could feel not only the vibrations,
but also the impassioned rhythm,
the throb, and the urge of the music.
The intertwined and intermingling vibrations
from different instruments enchanted me.
I could actually distinguish the cornets,
the roll of the drums,
deep toned violas and violins
singing in exquisite unison.
How the lovely speech of the violins
flowed and plowed over the deepest tones
of the other instruments.
When the human voices leapt up,
thrilling from the surge of harmony,
I recognized them instantly as voices.
I felt the chorus grow more exultant,
more ecstatic, upcurving,
swift, and flamelike
until my heart almost stood still.
The women's voices seemed an embodiment
of all the angelic voices
rushing in a harmonious flood
of beautiful and inspiring sound.
The great chorus throbbed against my fingers
with poignant pause and flow.
Then all the instruments and voices together
burst forth an ocean of heavenly vibration
and died away,
like winds when the atom is spent,
ending in a delicate shower
of sweet notes.
Of course, this was not "hearing," but
I do know that the tones and harmonies
conveyed to me moods of
great beauty and majesty.
I also sensed, or thought I did,
the tender sounds of nature
that sing into my hand:
swaying reeds,
and winds,
and the murmur of streams.
I have never been so enraptured before
by a multitude of tone vibrations.
As I listened with darkness and melody
and shadow and sound filling all the room,
I could not help remembering that
the great composer who poured forth
such a flood of sweetness into the world
was deaf like myself.
I marveled at the power
of his quenchless spirit
by which out of his pain he
wrought such joy for others.
And there I sat,
feeling with my hand
the magnificent symphony
which broke like a sea
upon the silent shores
of his soul and mine.
Let me thank you warmly for all the delight
which your beautiful music has brought
to my household and to me.
With kindest regards and best wishes,
I am sincerely yours,
Helen Keller.